ABOLFAZL HASHEMI

Office: MSEE 344, 501 Northwestern Ave., West Lafayette, Indiana 47907-2035

Phone: (765) 496-6040 \$\displant\text{Email: abolfazl@purdue.edu}\$ \$\displant\text{Website: https://abolfazlh.github.io}\$

CURRENT POSITION

Assistant Professor

Purdue University

August 2021 – present

Elmore Family School of Electrical and Computer Engineering

RESEARCH DESCRIPTION

My research interests include the study of Machine Learning, Online Learning, Learning in Games, and Networked/Distributed Decision-Making from the perspective of optimization. In doing so, we design efficient algorithms with mathematical guarantees to render practical deployment of learning-based systems possible under a variety of considerations such as limited resources, and robustness, and adversarial behaviors.

EDUCATION

Doctor of Philosophy (Ph.D.) , Electrical and Computer Engineering University of Texas at Austin, Austin, Texas, USA	2016 - 2020
Master of Science in Engineering (M.S.E.), Electrical and Computer Engineering University of Texas at Austin, Austin, Texas, USA	2014 - 2016
Bachelor of Science (B.S.), Electrical Engineering Sharif University of Technology, Tehran, Iran	2010 - 2014

PREVIOUS POSITIONS

Postdoctoral Fellow University of Texas at Austin Oden Institute for Computational Engineering and Sciences Advisors: Prof. Rachel Ward, Prof. Inderjit Dhillon, Prof. Ufuk Topcu	2020 - 2021
Graduate Research and Teaching Assistant University of Texas at Austin Department of Electrical and Computer Engineering Advisor: Prof. Haris Vikalo	2014 - 2020
Data Scientist Intern Cognitive Scale, Austin, Texas	Summer 2017

Undergraduate Research Intern

Hong Kong University of Science and Technology

Department of Electrical and Computer Engineering

Summer 2013

Host: Prof. Daniel Palomar

Undergraduate Research and Teaching Assistant

Sharif University of Technology
Department of Electrical Engineering

INVITED PRESENTATIONS

1. No-Regret Learning in Dynamic Stackelberg Games, Multi-Agent Dynamic Games workshop at at IEEE/RSJ International Conference on Intelligent Robots and Systems (IROS), Oct. 2023.

- 2. Theory-guided Methods for Private Federated Learning, SIAM Conference on Computational Science and Engineering, March 2023.
- 3. No-Regret Learning in Dynamic Stackelberg Games, Information Theory and Applications Workshop, Feb. 2023.
- 4. Generalization Bounds for Sparse Random Feature Expansions, SIAM Conference on Mathematics and Data Science (MDS), September 2022.
- 5. Faster Non-Convex Federated Learning via Global and Local Momentum, 2022 NSF TRIPODS PI Meeting, September 2022.
- 6. On the Convergence of Differentially Private Federated Learning on Non-Lipschitz Objectives via Clipping and Normalized Client Updates, Federated Learning One World Seminar, April 2022.
- 7. AI at Scale: Robustness and Security in Adversarial Environments, The Center for Education and Research in Information Assurance and Security (CERIAS), Purdue University, Oct. 2021.
- 8. Structured and Resource-Constrained Collaborative Learning, Center for Innovation in Control, Optimization, and Networks (ICON), Purdue University, Sep. 2021.
- 9. Structured and Resource-Constrained Collaborative Learning, Department of Computer Science, Purdue University, Sep. 2021.
- 10. Weak Submodular Optimization: Theory, Algorithm, Application, Department of Computer Science at UIUC, Feb. 2020.
- 11. Progressive Stochastic Greedy Sparse Reconstruction and Support Selection, 15th CSL student conference at UIUC, Feb. 2020.
- 12. Tutorial on Submodular Maximization, The Oden Institute for Computational Engineering and Sciences at UT Austin, Nov. 2019.
- 13. Tutorial on Submodular Minimization, The Oden Institute for Computational Engineering and Sciences at UT Austin, Oct. 2019.
- 14. Sparse Tensor Decomposition for Haplotype Assembly of Diploids and Polyploids, 12th CSL student conference at UIUC, Feb. 2017.

PUBLICATIONS

Journal Papers

- 1. Lauffer, N., Ghasemi, M., Hashemi, A., Savas, Y., Topcu, U., "No-Regret Learning in Dynamic Stackelberg Games," IEEE Transactions on Automatic Control, 2023.
- 2. Chellapandi, V., Upadhyay, A., Hashemi, A., Zak, S., "On the Convergence of Decentralized Federated Learning Under Imperfect Information Sharing," IEEE Control Systems Letters, 2023.
- 3. Upadhyay, A., Hashemi, A., "Improved Convergence Analysis and SNR Control Strategies for Federated Learning in the Presence of Noise," **IEEE Access**, 2023.
- 4. Kaya, E., Sahin, M., Hashemi, A., "Communication-Efficient Zeroth-Order Distributed Online Optimization: Algorithm, Theory, and Applications," IEEE Access, 2023.
- 5. Hashemi*, A., Schaeffer*, H., Shi*, B., Tran*, G., Ward*, R., "Generalization Bounds for Sparse Random Feature Expansions," Applied and Computational Harmonic Analysis, 2022.
- 6. Hashemi, A., Vikalo, H., de Veciana, G., "On the Benefits of Progressively Increasing Sampling Sizes in Stochastic Greedy Weak Submodular Maximization," IEEE Transactions on Signal Processing, 2022.

- 7. Ghasemi, M., Hashemi, A., Vikalo, H., Topcu, U., "Learning in Markov Decision Processes with Varying Rewards: High Probability Regret Bounds under Bandit Feedback and Unknown Horizon," **IEEE** Transactions on Automatic Control (conditionally accepted), 2022.
- 8. Hashemi, A., Shafipour, R., Vikalo, H., Mateos, G., "Towards Accelerated Greedy Sampling and Reconstruction of Bandlimited Graph Signals," Signal Processing, 2022.
- 9. Chen, Y., Hashemi, A., Vikalo, H., "Communication-Efficient Variance-Reduced Decentralized Stochastic Optimization over Time-Varying Directed Graphs," IEEE Transactions on Automatic Control, 2022.
- 10. Hashemi, A., Acharya*, A., Das*, R., Vikalo, H., Sanghavi, S., Dhillon, I., "On the Benefits of Multiple Gossip Steps in Communication-Constrained Decentralized Federated Learning," IEEE Transactions on Parallel and Distributed Systems, Special Section on Parallel and Distributed Computing Techniques for AI, ML, and DL, 2021.
- 11. Hashemi, A., Ghasemi, M., Vikalo, H., Topcu, U., "Randomized Greedy Sensor Selection: Leveraging Weak Submodularity," IEEE Transactions on Automatic Control, Jan. 2021.
- 12. Hashemi, A. and Vikalo, H., "Evolutionary Self-Expressive Models for Subspace Clustering," **IEEE Journal of Selected Topics in Signal Processing, Special Issue on Data Science: Robust Subspace Learning and Tracking,** vol. 12, no. 6, pp. 1534–1546, Dec. 2018.
- 13. Hashemi, A. and Vikalo, H., "Accelerated Orthogonal Least-Squares for Large-Scale Sparse Reconstruction," Digital Signal Processing, vol. 82, pp. 91–105, Nov. 2018.
- 14. Hashemi, A., Zhu, B., Vikalo, H., "Sparse Tensor Decomposition for Haplotype Assembly of Diploids and Polyploids," BMC Genomics, vol. 19, no. 4, pp. 1–15, Mar. 2018.

Conference Papers

- 1. Castillo, A., Kaya, E., Hashemi, A., "High Probability Guarantees for Submodular Maximization via Boosted Stochastic Greedy," 57th Asilomar Conference on Signals, Systems, and Computers, 2023.
- 2. Hashemi, A., "Predictive Estimation for Reinforcement Learning with Time-Varying Reward Functions," 57th Asilomar Conference on Signals, Systems, and Computers, 2023.
- 3. Upadhyay, A., Hashemi, A., "Noisy Communication of Information in Federated Learning: An Improved Convergence Analysis," 57th Asilomar Conference on Signals, Systems, and Computers, 2023.
- 4. Kaya*, E., Sahin*, M., Hashemi, A., "Communication-Constrained Exchange of Zeroth-Order Information with Application to Collaborative Target Tracking," International Conference on Acoustics, Speech and Signal Processing (ICASSP), 2023.
- 5. Chen, Y., Hashemi, A., Vikalo, H., "Accelerated Decentralized Stochastic Non-Convex Optimization over Directed Networks," International Conference on Acoustics, Speech and Signal Processing (ICASSP), 2023.
- 6. Yalcinkaya, D., Benan Unal, H., Raman, S., Hashemi, A., Dharmakumar, R., Sharif, B., "Data-adapted Neural Network Denoisers as a Regularization Engine for Low-latency Image Reconstruction in Accelerated Cardiac Perfusion MRI," 31st Annual Meeting of ISMRM, 2023.
- 7. Hibbard, M., Hashemi, A., Tanaka, T., Topcu, U., "Randomized Greedy Algorithms for Sensor Selection in Large-Scale Satellite Constellations," American Control Conference (ACC), 2023.
- 8. Das, R., Hashemi, A., Sanghavi, S., Dhillon, I., "DP-NormFedAvg: Normalizing Client Updates for Privacy-Preserving Federated Learning," 14th International Workshop on Optimization for Machine Learning at NeurIPS, 2022.
- 9. Das, R., Hashemi*, A., Acharya*, A., Sanghavi, S., Dhillon, I., Topcu, U., "Faster Non-Convex Federated Learning via Global and Local Momentum," Conference on Uncertainty in Artificial Intelligence

(UAI), 2022.

- 10. Acharya, A., Hashemi, A., Jain, P., Sanghavi, S., Dhillon, I., Topcu, U., "Robust SGD via Block coordinate Geometric Median Descent," International Conference on Artificial Intelligence and Statistics (AISTATS), 2022.
- 11. Ghasemi*, M., Hashemi*, A., Vikalo, H., Topcu, U., "No-Regret Learning with High-Probability in Adversarial Markov Decision Processes," Conference on Uncertainty in Artificial Intelligence (UAI), 2021.
- 12. Ghasemi, M., Hashemi, A., Topcu, U., Vikalo, H., "Online Learning with Implicit Exploration in Episodic Markov Decision Processes," American Control Conference (ACC), 2021.
- 13. Savas, Y., Hashemi, A., Vinod, AP., Sadler, BM., Topcu, U., "Physical-Layer Security via Distributed Beam-forming in the Presence of Adversaries with Unknown Locations," International Conference on Acoustics, Speech and Signal Processing (ICASSP), 2021.
- 14. Chen, Y., Hashemi, A., Vikalo, H., "Decentralized Optimization on Time-Varying Directed Graphs under Communication Constraints," International Conference on Acoustics, Speech and Signal Processing (ICASSP), 2021.
- 15. Hashemi, A., Vikalo, H., de Veciana, G., "On the Performance-Complexity Tradeoff in Stochastic Greedy Weak Submodular Optimization," International Conference on Acoustics, Speech and Signal Processing (ICASSP), 2021.
- 16. Ghasemi, M., Hashemi, A., Vikalo, H., Topcu, U., "Identifying Low-Dimensional Structures in Markov Chains: A Nonnegative Matrix Factorization Approach," American Control Conference (ACC), 2020.
- 17. Ghasemi*, M., Hashemi*, A., Vikalo, H., Topcu, U., "On Submodularity of Quadratic Observation Selection in Constrained Networked Sensing Systems," American Control Conference (ACC), 2019.
- 18. Shafipour, R., Hashemi, A., Mateos, G., Vikalo, H., "Online Topology Inference from Streaming Stationary Graph Signals," Data Science Workshop (DSW), 2019.
- 19. Hashemi, A., Ghasemi, M., Vikalo, H., Topcu, U., "Submodular Observation Selection and Information Gathering for Quadratic Models," International Conference on Machine Learning (ICML), June 2019.
- 20. Hashemi, A. and Vikalo, H., "Evolutionary Subspace Clustering: Discovering Structure In Self-expressive Time-series Data," International Conference on Acoustic, Speech and Signal Processing, 2019.
- 21. Consul, S., Hashemi, A., Vikalo, H., "A MAP Framework for Support Recovery of Sparse Signals Using Orthogonal Least Squares," International Conference on Acoustic, Speech and Signal Processing (ICASSP), Brighton, 2019.
- 22. Hashemi*, A., Kilic*, O.F., Vikalo, H., "Near-Optimal Distributed Estimation for a Network of Sensing Units Operating Under Communication Constraints," Conference on Decision and Control (CDC), 2018.
- 23. Hashemi, A., Shafipour, R., Vikalo, H., Mateos, G., "A Novel Scheme for Support Identification and Iterative Sampling of Bandlimited Graph Signals," Global Conference on Signal and Information Processing (GlobalSIP), 2018.
- 24. Hashemi, A., Ghasemi, M., Vikalo, H., Topcu, U., "A Randomized Greedy Algorithm for Near-Optimal Sensor Scheduling in Large-Scale Sensor Networks," American Control Conference (ACC), 2018.
- 25. Hashemi, A., Shafipour, R., Vikalo, H., Mateos, G., "Sampling and Reconstruction of Graph Signals via Weak Submodularity and Semidefinite Relaxation," International Conference on Acoustic, Speech and Signal Processing (ICASSP), 2018.

- 26. Hashemi, A., Zhu, B., Vikalo, H., "Sparse Tensor Decomposition for Haplotype Assembly of Diploids and Polyploids," International Workshop on Computational Network Biology: Modeling, Analysis, Control (CNB-MAC), 2017.
- 27. Hashemi, A. and Vikalo, H., "Sparse Recovery via Branch and Bound Least-Squares," International Conference on Acoustic, Speech and Signal Processing (ICASSP), 2017.
- 28. Hashemi, A. and Vikalo, H., "Sparse Linear Regression via Generalized Orthogonal Least-Squares," Global Conference on Signal and Information Processing (GlobalSIP), 2016.

SCHOLASTIC HONORS

- Outstanding Reviewer of ICML 2020, August 2020
- 1 of 4 selected as an invited student speaker at 15th CSL conference at UIUC, Machine Learning for Signal Processing session, February 2020
- Selected as the Schmidt Science Fellows Award nominee from UT Austin, 2019
- Best student paper award finalist, American Control Conference, June 2018
- 1 of 4 selected as an invited student speaker at 12th CSL conference at UIUC, Bioinformatics and Computational Genomics session, February 2017
- Travel awards for ICML 2019, ACC 2019, ACC 2018, CNB-MAC 2017, ICASSP 2017, GlobalSIP 2016
- Inclusive Classrooms Leadership Certificate, UT Austin, February 2015
- Professional Teaching Assistant Certificate, UT Austin, August 2014
- Qualied as an Exceptional Talent eligible to enter Graduate Studies without entrance exam, Sharif University of Technology, 2013
- Ranked 79th among more than 277,000 participants in the Nationwide University Entrance Exam for B.Sc. degree, 2010
- Recipient of Iranian National Elite Foundation fellowship, 2010-2014

TEACHING EXPERIENCE

Purdue University

Elmore Family School of Electrical and Computer Engineering

Instructor

Fall 2023
Spring 2023
Spring 2023
Fall 2022
Fall 2022

Spring 2022

Fall 2021

University of Texas at Austin

Department of Electrical and Computer Engineering

• ECE 20001: Electrical Engineering Fundamental I

• ECE 20001: Electrical Engineering Fundamental I

Graduate Teaching Assistant

•	Statistical Machine Learning	Fall 2019

• Estimation Theory Fall 2017

Department of Electrical Engineering Undergraduate Teaching Assistant	
• Digital Signal Processing	Fall 2013
• Communication Systems	Fall 2013
• Principles of Electronics	Fall 2013
• Principles of Electronics	Spring 2013
• Computer Architecture	Spring 2013
• Logic Circuits	Spring 2013
• Analog Circuits	Spring 2013
• Electromagnetism	Fall 2012

Spring 2015

Fall 2014

ADVISING

Current Ph.D. Students

- Antesh Upadhyay (since December 2021)
- Ege Kaya (since August 2022)

• Digital Signal Processing

• Digital Signal Processing

Sharif University of Technology

- Andres C Castillo (since August 2022)
- Mehmet Berk Sahin (since August 2022), Co-adviser: Prof. Behzad Sharif
- Sang Bin Moon (since August 2022), Co-adviser: Prof. Jan-Anders Mansson
- Dilek Yalcinkaya (since August 2022), Co-advised with Prof. Behzad Sharif

Current M.Sc. Students with Thesis

• Sravani Ramishetty (since December 2021)

Other Advising Roles

- Actively advising undergraduates through programs such as SURF and Summer Stay
- Serving on the committee of eight PhD. students.
- Faculty advisor for Purdue RoboMaster Club, Plurimos LLP, and ECE COMPES.

SERVICES AT THE PURDUE UNIVERSITY

• Member of the SMI committee for PMP students	October 2022 – present
\bullet Member of the graduate admissions committee, CNSIP and CE areas	December 2021 – present
• Co-organizer of ICON Seminar Series	Spring 2022
• Co-organizer of two ECE Seminars	Fall 2022

PROFESSIONAL MEMBERSHIPS AND SERVICES

Grant Proposal Panels

• NSF Panelist, 2023

Conference/Workshop Organizer

- Panelist in TRIPODS Postdoc Workshop, Toyota Technological Institute at Chicago August, 2023
- EnCORE Institute Sessions on "Distributed Learning and Decision-Making" at ITA 2023

Technical Program Committee

• Networks and Communication Systems Technical Committee IEEE Control Systems Society

October 2022 – present

2020

Conference Area Chair

• 26th International Conference on Artificial Intelligence and Statistics (AISTATS)	2023
• International Conference on Images, Signals, and Computing (ICISC)	2023
• International Workshop on Signal Processing Advances in Wireless Communications (SPAWC)	2020
• International Multi-Conference on Computing in the Global Information Technology	2019
• International Conference on Mobile, Hybrid, and Online Learning	2019
• International Conference on Advanced Engineering Computing and Applications in Sciences	2018
• International Multi-Conference on Computing in the Global Information Technology	2018

Professional Society Memberships

- Institute of Electrical and Electronics Engineers (IEEE), Signal Processing Society 2016 - present 2016 - present
- Society for Industrial and Applied Mathematics (SIAM)

Journal Reviews

- IEEE Control Systems Letters
- IEEE Signal Processing Magazine
- IEEE Transactions on Signal Processing
- IEEE Signal Processing Letters
- IEEE Transactions on Signal and Information Processing over Networks
- Elsevier Signal Processing
- IET Signal Processing
- IEEE Transactions on Robotics
- IEEE Transactions on Control of Networked Systems
- IEEE Transactions on Automatic Control
- Automatica
- IEEE Transactions on Wireless Communications
- IEEE Transactions on Communications
- IEEE Transactions on Cybernetics
- IEEE Journal of Selected Areas in Information Theory
- IEEE Access
- Information Sciences
- SIAM Journal on Scientific Computing

- Nature Scientific Reports
- PLOS One
- Taylor and Francis Journal on Forensic Sciences Research

Conference Reviews

• International Conference on Acoustics, Speech and Signal Processing (ICASSP)	2023
• International Conference on Artificial Intelligence and Statistics (AISTATS)	2021
• International Conference on Machine Learning (ICML)	2020,2021,2022,2023
• Conference on Neural Information Processing Systems (NeurIPS)	2020, 2022
• American Control Conference (ACC)	2020,2021,2022
• International Symposium on Information Theory (ISIT)	2020
• International Workshop on Signal Processing Advances in Wireless Communicati	ions (SPAWC) 2020
• Conference on Decision and Control (CDC)	2018,2023
• International Conference on Image Processing (ICIP)	2022, 2023

SHORT BIO

Abolfazl Hashemi received the B.Sc. degree in Electrical Engineering from the Sharif University of Technology, Iran, in July 2014, and the M.S.E. and Ph.D. degrees in Electrical and Computer Engineering from the University of Texas at Austin, USA, in May 2016 and August 2020, respectively. From August 2020 to August 2021 he was a Postdoctoral Scholar at the Oden Institute for Computational Engineering and Sciences at the University of Texas at Austin. Since August 2021, he has been an Assistant Professor at the Elmore Family School of Electrical and Computer Engineering at Purdue University. Abolfazl was the 2019 Schmidt Science Fellows Award nominee from UT Austin, and the recipient of the Iranian national elite foundation fellowship and a best student paper award finalist at the 2018 American Control Conference. His research interests include optimization for machine learning, signal processing, and control.

Last Update: 21st Jul, 2023